John Cowper Powys Papers
John Cowper Powys Papers
1890-1972
Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963.
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the British novelist, poet, author. Collection includes correspondence (1927-1965); manuscript notebooks containing holograph fragments of essays, novels, plays, poems, prefaces (1890-1966); and memorabilia including clippings, pamphlets, and a Powys family photograph album. Correspondents include Graham Ackroyd, Fred Bason, Norman Denny, Lucile Grebenc, Warren Penn Kime, George L. Lewin, Laurence Pollack, Dorothy M. Richardson, Asta Fleming Sullivan, Sven-Erik Tāckmark, and Clifford Tolchard.
149531
Biographical History
John Cowper Powys (1872-1963) was an English essayist, novelist and poet.
Powys was born in Shirley, Derbyshire, England, on October 8, 1872. He received his education at Sherborne Preparatory School and later at Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, where he earned his degreee in history.In 1896 and 1899, Powys published two volumes of poetry, Odes and Other Poems and Poems, respectively. Then, for several years he was primarily occupied with lecturing, first for the Oxford and Cambridge Extension, for whom he gave his first American lecture in 1910, and later on his own.
In 1915 his first novel, Wood and Stone, appeared. Two years later, his third volume of poetry, Mandragora, was published in America, followed by Samphire in 1922. From that point on his prolific output of essays, novels and poems continued until 1980, his eighty-eighth year.
John Cowper Powys married Margaret Alice Lyon on April 9, 1898, and they had one child, a son. Powys died June 17, 1963.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Cowper Powys Papers consist of correspondence, writings and memorabilia. The materials date from 1890-1972.
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically and includes letters to/from Powys as well as third-party correspondence discussing Powys.
Writings consists primarily of unpublished fragments and notebooks of essays, novels, plays, poems, and prefaces. Also included here are Powys' letters compiled by Penn Kime in book form, and a typescript of Llewelyn Powys' Swiss Essays.
Memorabilia contains newspaper clippings, two published pamphlets on John Cowper Powys and the Powys family, and a Powys family photograph album.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Writings are arranged first by type and then by title.
Related Material
Other John Cowper Powys letters exist in the
Eric Wilson Barker Papers
and the
Edmund B. Chaffee Papers
, and in the papers of Professor A. E. Johnson in the Syracuse University Archives.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Ackroyd, Graham.; Bason, Frederick T.; Denny, Norman, 1901-1982.; Grebenc, Lucile.; Kime, Warren Penn, 1919-; Lewin, George L.; Powys, John Cowper, 1872-1963.; Sullivan, Asta Fleming.; Tackmark, Sven-Erik, 1916-; Pollock, Laurence.; Richardson, Dorothy M. (Dorothy Miller), 1873-1957.; Tolchard, Clifford, 1908-; Authors, English.; English literature, 20th century.; Novelists, English.; Poets, English.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Notebooks.; Photograph albums.; Poems.; Scripts (documents); Authors.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marian Powys Grey, 1964 and purchase, 1962-1973.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1927-1965; undated (Box 1)
  - Ackroyd, Graham, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Bason, Fred, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Denny, Norman, 1946-1951; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Fleming, Asta, 1933-1939; 1953-1961; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Grebenc, Lucile, 1935-1939 (Box 1)
  - Harker, Brian, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Kime, Warren Penn Jr., 1943-1959; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Lewin, George L., 1939-1960; undated; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Odle, Rose Isserlis, 1956-1962 (Box 1)
  - Petterson, Sven-Eric, 1937-1943 (Box 1)
  - Pollinger, Lawrence, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Powys, Theodore Francis, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Priestley, J. B., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Ravenel, St. Julien, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
  - Richardson, Dorothy M., 1953 (Box 1)
  - Tolchard, Clifford, 1947-1960; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Wilkinson, Louis, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1927-1929; 1933,; 1938,; 1947,; 1951-1955,; undated (Box 1)
    Includes the following: Cate, Garth; Curtis (Mrs.); Grey, Marion Powys; Harker, Brian; Lorring, Pierre; Milkman, Jerome; Roberts, Lester; Russell, Oliver John; Schuster, Max Lincoln; Tackmark, [Sven Eric]; White, Katherine; several unidentified individuals
- Writings
  - Books
    - After My Fashion, 1980; published edition, Pan Books, London (Box 1)
    - Autobiography, 1934; fragment, holograph (Box 2)
    - In Spite Of, 1953; fragment, holograph, chapter 1, typescript carbon revised; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Mortal Strife, 1943; chapters 1-5, typescript carbon revised; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Morwyn, 1937; fragment, holograph (Box 2)
    - Owen Glendower, 1940; fragment, holograph; chapters 1-6 and 8, typescript carbon revised; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Rodmoor, fragment, holograph (Box 2)
    - Weymouth Sands, 1934; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - Wolf Solent, 1929; fragment, holograph; chapters 19-24, holograph; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Untitled [early novel], circa 1894; fragment, holograph; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Untitled [the life of a street girl], circa 1900; notebook, holograph (Box 3)
    - Untitled, circa 1904; two notebooks, holograph (Box 3)
  - Essays
    - "The Inhumanity of Liberal Protestantism", undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - "The New Paganism", circa 1910; notebook, holograph (Box 3)
    - On America, undated; fragment and notes, holograph (Box 3)
    - On being happy with a woman, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On contemplating life and death, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On Dorchester, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On Dostoievski, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On "The Ichthian Act", undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On Mr. James Flanders at Wealden, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On the purpose of life, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On Several Subjects – and From Several Points of View, circa 1894; notebook, holograph (Box 3)
    - On two sisters – Fanny and Lubie Howard, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On tyranny, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - On vivisection and fascism, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - What I expect from Life, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - What is Happiness, undated; fragment, holograph (Box 3)
    - Unidentified fragment, undated; holograph (Box 3)
  - Plays
    - The Idiot, 1922; Acts I-IV, holograph and typescript carbon; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - The Idiot, typescript carbon with notes (Box 4)
    - With Love Away, and other unpublished fragments and poems, circa 1894; 3 notebooks, holograph; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - With Love Away, Transcription by Paul Roberts, 1993; typescript (Box 4)
    - Untitled, circa 1894; five notebooks, holograph (Box 5)
  - Poetry
    - Burpham Journals, circa 1909; circa 1919; 2 notebooks; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Cambridge and Southwick Journals, circa 1890-1896; 8 notebooks; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Cambridge and Southwick Journals, circa 1890-1896; 1 notebook (Box 6)
    - Samphire, circa 1912; notebook, holograph (Box 6)
    - Samphire, circa 1922; typescript of published material (Box 6)
  - Prefaces
    - To the May Chesshire Letters, circa 1935; fragment, holograph (Box 6)
    - To Stern, circa 1948; fragments, unpublished holograph, typescript carbon; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letters from a Modern Welsh Merlin, John Cowper Powys to Penn Kime, 1964; typescript of letters between Powys and Kime, with foreword by Kime (Box 6)
    - Swiss Essays by Llewelyn Powys, 1947; typescript carbon (Box 6)
- Memorabilia
  - Copy negatives from photograph album (not all-inclusive) (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings and autograph, 1955-1972 (Box 6)
  - Philobiblon, no. 8, published by Colgate University Press, Winter 1966 (Box 6)
  - Photograph album, Powys family (Oversize 1)
  - The Powys Family, by Littleton circa Powys, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook of clippings (Oversize 2)